Guide to the Richard Brinsley Sheridan Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Richard Brinsley Sheridan collection
1769-1814
GEN MSS 284
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.5
(1 box)
The collection contains letters by, to and concerning Sheridan, including letters by Sheridan to Robert Barclay, the Duke of Bedford, and Samuel Whitehead; and writings by Sheridan, including four manuscript copies of the School for Scandal, one with annotations and corrections in Sheridan's hand; a holograph draft of a comic opera, The Foresters; and notes for Affectation, a projected comedy.
Other Storage Formats: 9 volumes
Sheridan, Richard Brinsley, 1751-1816
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Richard Brinsley Sheridan, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection. Materials incorporated into the collection prior to July 1997 have been organized into three series: Correspondence, Writings, and Other Papers.
Dramatists, English -- 18th century; English drama -- 18th century; Barclay, Robert, 1833-1876; Bedford, Francis Russell, Duke of, 1765-1802; Sheridan, Richard Brinsley, 1751-1816; Whitehead, Samuel
- Correspondence, Series I
  - BANNISTER, JOHN
    - ALS to Samuel Cartwright, 1830 Feb 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Gift, 1954.
  - GRAHAM, J.
    - ALS to an unidentified recipient, London (Box 1, Folder 2)
      1 p. with endorsement.
      22 cm.
      With a note by Richard Brinsley
      Sheridan.
  - NICHOLLS, SARAH
    - ALS to Richard Brinsley Sheridan, London, 1810 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      1 p. with address, 20 cm.
      Sheridan's maidservant writes to
      ask for money on which to live
      while he is away from London.
  - PALMER, ROBERT
    - ALS to the management of Drury Lane [Richard Brinsley Sheridan], London, 1815 Jul 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      1 p. 21 cm.
      Requesting continuance of his
      employment at the theatre.
  - SHERIDAN, ELIZABETH (LINLEY)
    - 3 ALS and 1 AL (in the third person) to Richard Peake (Box 1, Folder 5)
      4 p. with addresses. 18-19 cm.
      Concerning personal financial
      matters.
  - SHERIDAN, RICHARD BRINSLEY BUTLER
    - ALS to Robert Barclay, London (Box 1, Folder 6)
      1 p. with address, 24 cm.
      Paper watermarked 1805.
    - Franked piece of paper addressed to "Miss Beddyke, 10 Grosvenor Place", London, 1810 Jun 21 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - ALS to Francis Russell, Duke of Bedford (the Marquis of Tavistock), 1808 Aug 19 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      1 p. with envelope.
      Gift, 1948.
    - 2 ALS to Mr. Burgess, Farnham, [1814? Nov] (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Both letters with address. Paper of
      first letter watermarked 1813.
      Engraving of a portrait of R.B.
      Sheridan laid in folder.
      Gift, 1937.
    - ALS to "Dear Burgess", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Purchase, 1964.
    - ALS to Thomas Holloway, [London], [1807] Nov 13 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      1 p. with address, 23 cm.
      Draft of Holloway's reply on p. [3]
      Concerning the debts of Mr. Shaw,
      orchestra conductor at Drury Lane
      Theatre.
    - ALS to [Richard Peake?], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      1 p. 24 cm.
      Gift.
    - ALS to Mr. Peake (?), Winchester, 1797 Jun 18 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - ALS to Mr. Shaw, Chancery Lane, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13a)
    - 2 ALS to Hester (Ogle) Sheridan, London, 1800, 1804 (Box 1, Folder 13b)
      Letters to his wife dated 1800 September 5 and "seven 1804." Accompanied by letter from Clare Sheridan, 1937 December 18 to George Nettleton, Yale College Office of the Dean, and reply from Nettleton (copy) dated 1938 January 3. Gift, 1937.
    - ALS to Charles Ward, 1814 Sep 21 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Purchase, 1962.
    - ADft. of letter to Samuel Whitehead, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Purchase, 1959.
    - ALS to an unidentified recipient, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
      1 p.
      Gift, 1944.
- Writings, Series II
  - SHERIDAN, RICHARD BRINSLEY BUTLER
    - AFFECTATION: autograph manuscript notes for a projected comedy, written on 28 pages and the endpapers of a small, leather-bound memorandum book. (Box 1, Folder 17)
      11.5 x 18 cm. In a red cloth slip
      case.
    - THE CARAVAN: manuscript play in an unidentified hand with alterations in the hand of Sheridan.
      40 p. 15 x 23.5 cm. Bound in three-
      quarter green leather.
      Autograph of J.W. Connolly, Oct. 12,
      1858.
      Gift, 1947.
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Volume 1
    - THE CRITIC, OR A TRAGEDY REHEARS'D: manuscript prompt copy in an unidentified hand, with a few manuscript corrections by Sheridan., [1781?]
      124 p. 23 cm.
      Presentation inscription from
      Sheridan to Mrs. Crewe; bookplate
      of Sophie Hall-Walker.
      Bound in 3/4 green morocco.
      Purchase, 1954.
      See: Volume 2
    - THE FORESTERS: autograph manuscript draft of a comic opera, [1781-1795] (Box 1, Folder 18)
      9 leaves, inlaid. 18-24 cm.
      The play was never produced.
    - PISCATORY PARTY. IN COMMEMORATION OF ISAAC WALTON. Autograph manuscript, signed, of the rules and regulations drawn up by Sheridan and presented to the Walton & Cotton Club. Probably compiled sometime before 1803.
      10 p.
      Accompanied by an autograph note
      stating the authenticity of the
      manuscript and signed by W[illiam]
      Dunn, 22 Charlotte Street, Bedford
      Square, May 9, 1814.
      Bound by Sangorski and Sutcliffe in
      full green morocco with special
      title-page, transcript, and extract
      of a description of the manuscript
      which appeared in The Field, Sept.
      28, 1907.
      See: Volume 3
    - THE SCHOOL FOR SCANDAL: manuscript made by four copyists with numerous corrections in Sheridan's hand and a note signed by him, submitting the play for licensing to William Chetwynd early in 1777.
      140 p. 19 x 24 cm.
      With David Garrick's Prologue, and
      George Colman's Epilogue.
      AN signed George Chetwynd, on fly-
      leaf. Grandon Hall, [England] Sept.
      10, 1834.
      This manuscript was damaged by fire
      in the bookbinding establishment of
      Fairburn, on February 26, 1834; the
      leaves of the ms were subsequently
      inlaid and bound in blind tooled
      russia with the arms of Sir George
      Chetwynd stamped on front and back
      covers.
      Three engraved portraits (2 of
      Sheridan and 1 of Mrs. Frances
      Abington) and several contemporary
      newspaper clippings bound in as
      preliminary leaves.
      Autographs of Wm. Chetwynd and
      Frances Brookes; bookplates of Sir
      George Chetwynd, Robert J. Collier,
      and Augustin Daly.
      See: Volume 4
    - "THE SCHOOL FOR SCANDAL: A Comedy. As perform'd at the Theatre Royal Drury Lane...1777" Manuscript copy in an unidentified handwriting, probably used as a promptbook. The notes of authorship at the head of the "Prologue" and of the "Epilogue" are in Sheridan's autograph. Formerly the property of Albinia Bertie Hobart, Countess of Buckinghamshire, with her signature, "Albinia Buckinghamshire".
      Bound in three-quarter red morocco.
      p. i-iv; 1-215; [i-ii].
      Purchase, 1936.
      See: Volume 5
    - THE SCHOOL FOR SCANDAL: manuscript copy in a contemporary unidentified hand.
      199 ff. 22.5 cm.
      With David Garrick's Prologue and
      The name of the former owner,
      Charles Laurence, is lettered in a
      Gothic hand on flyleaf.
      Bound in polished calf.
      Gift, 1951.
      See: Volume 6
    - THE SCHOOL FOR SCANDAL: Manuscript copy, written in a contemporary hand.
      141 folio l. written on one side of
      the paper.
      The paper is watermarked 1795.
      Gift, 1932.
      See: Volume 7
- Other Papers, Series III
  - SHERIDAN, RICHARD BRINSLEY BUTLER
    - ALGEBRA 1769: autograph manuscript notebook kept by Sheridan while a student at Harrow., n.d.
      146 p. 16 x 19.5 cm. Bound in
      contemporary vellum. Lettered on
      spine: Alg. Vol I. R. B. S.
      "Charles Brinsley, the son of
      Sheridan by his second marriage,
      has recorded that his father left
      behind him 'six copybooks each
      filled with notes and references to
      mathematics, carefully written by
      Mr. S. at an early age'..."
      See: Volume 8
    - MEMORANDUM FOR THE PRIVATE BOXES AT DRURY LANE THEATRE: autograph manuscript.
      Note on verso of second leaf, in an
      unidentified hand: "Mr. Sheridans
      memorandum...made at Hommenley in
      Janry 1797"
      Accompanied by two floor plans,
      entitled "Design for an additional
      private box and setting back the
      boxes" and "Plan of the orchestra
      boxes."
      See: Volume 9
    - Notes for a speech on the Volunteers, made before the House of Commons: autograph manuscript, [London], [1803 Aug 10] (Box 1, Folder 19)
      3 p. 9-12 cm.
      Speech published in Speeches of
      Sheridan, London, Patrick Martin,
      1816; V, 240.
      Purchase, 1955.
- Volumes, n.d.
  - THE CARAVAN: manuscript play in an unidentified hand with alterations in the hand of Sheridan. (Box Volume 1)
  - THE CRITIC, OR A TRAGEDY REHEARS'D: manuscript prompt copy in an unidentified hand, with a few manuscript corrections by Sheridan., [1781?] (Box Volume 2)
  - PISCATORY PARTY. IN COMMEMORATION OF ISAAC WALTON. Autograph manuscript, signed, of the rules and regulations drawn up by Sheridan and presented to the Walton & Cotton Club. Probably compiled sometime before 1803. (Box Volume 3)
  - THE SCHOOL FOR SCANDAL: manuscript made by four copyists with numerous corrections in Sheridan's hand and a note signed by him, submitting the play for licensing to William Chetwynd early in 1777. (Box Volume 4)
  - "THE SCHOOL FOR SCANDAL: A Comedy. As perform'd at the Theatre Royal Drury Lane...1777" Manuscript copy in an unidentified handwriting, probably used as a promptbook. The notes of authorship at the head of the "Prologue" and of the "Epilogue" are in Sheridan's autograph. Formerly the property of Albinia Bertie Hobart, Countess of Buckinghamshire, with her signature, "Albinia Buckinghamshire". (Box Volume 5)
  - THE SCHOOL FOR SCANDAL: manuscript copy in a contemporary unidentified hand. (Box Volume 6)
  - THE SCHOOL FOR SCANDAL: Manuscript copy, written in a contemporary hand. (Box Volume 7)
  - ALGEBRA 1769: autograph manuscript notebook kept by Sheridan while a student at Harrow., n.d. (Box Volume 8)
  - MEMORANDUM FOR THE PRIVATE BOXES AT DRURY LANE THEATRE: autograph manuscript. (Box Volume 9)